Alexis Wirtz: I'll try to remember what I said.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Oh, you talked about the behavioral sleep changes?
Alexis Wirtz: Yes. Yeah.
Alexis Wirtz: So, for family, what we look for is medication compliance in a patient that could trigger an acute decompensation. The early behavioral indica… indicators before manic episodes, I said we look for sleep changes.
Alexis Wirtz: That could be for mania, decreased need for sleep, feeling energized on less sleep, or not sleeping at all.
Alexis Wirtz: With that, we look for energy and goal-directed activity. For mania, it could be increased productivity, multitasking, impulsive projects or tasks that they weren't working on previously.
Alexis Wirtz: We also look at speech and communication patterns in patients who come into the emergency room. With mania, we can see increased frequency, speed, tangential thought processes, leading to, you know.
Alexis Wirtz: Longer thoughts that aren't necessarily connecting.
Alexis Wirtz: We look for spending or risk-taking behaviors.
Alexis Wirtz: As well as social rhythm disruption. This is a big one for hospitalization as well with mania, and by that I'm meaning a change in their normal pattern. Either they're not showing up to work, they're not able to keep up with their relationships, they're not able to keep up with the task of their daily living that they were prior able to.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Hmm.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Okay,
Laura L. Nwanebu: My next question would be, does the gap between appointments ever cause you to, like, miss something between, you know, earlier.
Laura L. Nwanebu: You know…
Alexis Wirtz: Gap between appointments, meaning a patient missed follow-up and has.
Laura L. Nwanebu: longer betrayed Between each follow-up, in between the previous one to the next one.
Alexis Wirtz: So, with patients that usually, if they've had a recent hospitalization, and they need higher
Alexis Wirtz: Follow-up will have closer follow-ups, and those follow-ups are, lengthened as they do well and better.
Alexis Wirtz: So we usually try to monitor patients who have had need for hospitalization more closely. So, in terms of gaps between follow-ups, if they miss an appointment or they aren't able to make the appointment after hospitalization, 100% we could see decompensation if this also goes with
Alexis Wirtz: You know, not taking medications, or wasn't able to get the refill, because we'll just give a bridge of medication until they can make that follow-up, if that makes sense.
Alexis Wirtz: I'm not sure I answered what you need, though.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah, a follow-up question. How'd you get the data? The sleep activities, the behavior? How'd you get the data from them? Do you just ask them?
Alexis Wirtz: Paul, I'll see you in a bit, okay?
Alexis Wirtz: Sorry.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah, I was asking, how'd you get the data? Like, there are sleep activities, there are behavioral changes, how'd you get those?
Alexis Wirtz: So for all our evaluations, one, this is a part of general questions that we ask any patient who comes to the emergency department, that if they're presenting with symptoms, we do a whole interview slew. And so we have to ask every single patient all these questions and many, many more. And part of our interview skills are
Alexis Wirtz: Taking what we see, what the patient tells us, and then also we'll ask collateral, which is a family member, a friend, someone that,
Alexis Wirtz: what we would like is that they live with, they know, or they follow up with closely, and then we also ask all these questions to that collateral contact to see if it matches, or what's different. And then we make an assessment based on everything.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: So, that's a great response, honestly. If you received, like, a one-page behavioral summary of…
Laura L. Nwanebu: your patience before sections. Would that be useful, or would it be, like, so much information to process?
Alexis Wirtz: Would this be outpatient specifically you're talking about between.
Laura L. Nwanebu: you know, point…
Alexis Wirtz: That's…
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah, between appointments. Let's say they have an appointment tomorrow, and you receive the report by today, by midnight.
Alexis Wirtz: Yeah, and you can read.
Laura L. Nwanebu: before…
Alexis Wirtz: were the appointments.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Exactly, a trend with all their activities, sleep, you know, behavioral changes.
Alexis Wirtz: So… 100%, the more information we have, the better.
Alexis Wirtz: So I would definitely review that if I was in the outpatient setting as a provider. What I will say is that, like, part of our interview is I have to ask everything again. So it wouldn't necessarily decrease the length of visit, but 100%, if there's collateral involved and more questions than the patient tells me during the visit, we could catch things that are potentially missed.
Alexis Wirtz: If they aren't as open or providing that information.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Hmm.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Boy, this is great.
Laura L. Nwanebu: specific, patient data from… from your experience, would you…
Laura L. Nwanebu: Like to get from this one-page summary.
Alexis Wirtz: What would be best for me personally, and I feel like we'd have to ask… we'll ask Skylar during our next appointment, but integration into the electronical medical record.
Alexis Wirtz: Is the most critical thing for me.
Alexis Wirtz: Because not only can I see it if I'm the provider at that follow-up, but it can be stored there, and we can monitor it for future visits. And if there's more information, then we have a data collection, right, of this patient's normal behaviors and activities, and catch things that
Alexis Wirtz: may be more minute that we wouldn't have caught until the behaviors escalate if we have this track record. Let's see.
Alexis Wirtz: So really, like, integration between any medical record system, and if we can refer back easily, is the best, so that we don't lose this information.
Alexis Wirtz: timely manner would probably be, like, if there's any time constraints, to review the data. So, like you said, sending it either the night before or…
Alexis Wirtz: I'm the… Patience.
Alexis Wirtz: Let's see… I don't know, I think that would be the biggest thing.
Alexis Wirtz: if… I don't know if this is too broad, or we even have this,
Alexis Wirtz: What do you call, like…
Alexis Wirtz: if this data or tool would be available, but what I always find, or think would be really helpful.
Alexis Wirtz: I say we're receiving all this extra information, somehow the system could alert us.
Alexis Wirtz: prior to the appointment, if there's any real risk or trigger that's changed from their behavior, just to say an extra, hey, you need to look into this. Like, this is out of the normal scope for X, Y, and Z.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Mmm… Okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Awesome.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah.
Alexis Wirtz: Yeah.
Laura L. Nwanebu: So, I'm just gonna give you a briefody of what I'm working on, so you could
Laura L. Nwanebu: You know, tell me your imputes about it.
Alexis Wirtz: Amazing.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah, so…
Alexis Wirtz: Okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: I'm working on a passive collecting system.
Laura L. Nwanebu: That takes the behavioral patterns of bipolar patients.
Laura L. Nwanebu: And give psychiatrists or clinicians, like, a one-page summary of
Laura L. Nwanebu: behavioral data. They don't have to log in their emotion. It uses phenotyping. It does that passively. And it sends all those data to the physician.
Alexis Wirtz: Okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: And talking about the alert system is something I never thought of.
Alexis Wirtz: Mmm!
Laura L. Nwanebu: You know, yeah, and I really… it's something I really want to incorporate to the idea, because it makes a lot of more impact.
Laura L. Nwanebu: you know.
Alexis Wirtz: Yeah.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah.
Alexis Wirtz: I think that, for me, the most helpful things for us is touchpoints, right? Like, it seems like with you trying to alert us with this extra information is amazing, and it's another touchpoint. And if we have multiple summaries over multiple visits.
Alexis Wirtz: Those are more touchpoints, and so really that alert, if something is out of range, is just another way the system could help us say, hey, take a closer look at this.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Wow, okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: And one last question.
Alexis Wirtz: Of course!
Laura L. Nwanebu: What would be a concern for, like, what would you think would be a concern for the patient or the, you know, the clinician when it comes to trusting this
Laura L. Nwanebu: Technology.
Alexis Wirtz: I think… How the information is gathered, and…
Alexis Wirtz: Is… is really important in terms of the types of questions that are asked, like, if…
Alexis Wirtz: I guess what I'm trying to say, I don't really know if I'm going to explain this right, but there's a lot of nuance and interpretation that we learn with interviews in how to gather information, and then take the tools that we have to extrapolate what that means.
Alexis Wirtz: And so I could find that if we are… potentially…
Alexis Wirtz: if it just becomes another data set that, like, is yes or no, or there's not enough information on it, it could be a bit tedious, and maybe not as helpful. Not saying your set will be, but I could say maybe that would be another thing.
Alexis Wirtz: I don't know. I don't think I answered that very well.
Laura L. Nwanebu: No, it's okay.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Yeah, I have gathered a couple of points that are so useful with my research, and thank you so much for your time.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Lastly, Do you mind if I… cause I…
Laura L. Nwanebu: I'm trying to view this idea and make a pitch. Do you mind being a clinical advisor?
Alexis Wirtz: Sure, no problem at all. And I can discuss with you back and forth and help you with any questions that you have, and we can try to make it, you know, continue to… if you have any more questions, or if you want to run through it… To the best of my ability, I'll help you.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Okay, thank you so much.
Alexis Wirtz: Yeah, of course. And when Skyward gets back as well, I know that she'll be willing to work on the project, too. I think this is really great.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Thank you so much, thank you.
Alexis Wirtz: Yeah. Yeah, of course. Feel free to email me anytime, and as you go through it, we're always available, okay?
Laura L. Nwanebu: Okay.
Alexis Wirtz: Yeah, it's great meeting you.
Laura L. Nwanebu: Same, it was awesome meeting you. Thank you for the information. Thank you.
Alexis Wirtz: Of course. And if you want to have another follow-up when she gets back, just shoot us an email, okay?
Laura L. Nwanebu: I will. Yeah, I will.
Alexis Wirtz: You can come in. Have a great day.
Laura L. Nwanebu: You too, have a great day. Thank you.
Alexis Wirtz: Bye. Oh, thank you. Hello!